Brice ARGENSON

Developer



Mr. Argenson is a graduate of SUPINFO International University. With seven years of industry experience as a software developer, he has worked with a broad range of Java and Web technologies. Throughout his career, he has developed and maintained software systems for logistical, financial, educational and social media sectors among others. He has also animated many trainings about Java technologies (Java SE, Java EE, Android...), Web technologies (HTML5, Advanced JavaScript...) and Agile methods (XP, Scrum).

Mr. Argenson puts a great deal of importance in building the right software and sees collaboration and compliance with good software development practices as the means to accomplish it.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Skills and techniques	Training
·	Design Patterns
Methodologies and practices	Scrum
Methodologies and practices	Continuous Integration
	Continuous Integration Continuous Delivery
	Refactoring
	User Stories
	Pair Programing
	Code Review
	Test-Driven Development (TDD)
Languages and tools	Java, JDBC, Servlet, JSP, JSF, Spring, Hibernate/JPA, EJB3, JAX-RS
	(REST), JAX-WS (SOAP), JUnit, Mockito, Groovy, Maven, Android
	JavaScript, jQuery, Angular, Node.js, Jasmine, HTML5 APIs
	Jenkins/Hudson, Bamboo, Git, Subversion, Eclipse, IntelliJ
	Google AppEngine, CloudBees, Heroku, AWS
	Docker, Fig
	Graphite, Logstash, Sensu
Databases and application	MySQL, MS SQL Server, Oracle, MongoDB
servers	Tomcat, Jetty, JBoss, Glassfish
Operating systems	Mac OS X
	• Linux
	Windows

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Nuance Communications

January 2014 until now

Montreal, Quebec

Software Developer / DevOps

In the mobility division, Mr. Argenson contributes to the development and to the improvement of the release cycle (DevOps) of the Nuance Cloud Services, a configurable, connected platform that transforms devices, services and mobile apps into intelligent personal assistants.

Main Missions:

- Implementation of automated acceptance tests with FitNesse
- Implementation of Continuous Integration processes
- Design and implementation of a Continuous Delivery pipeline with A/B testing
- Implementation of Continuous Monitoring
- Setup and maintenance of an Apache Cassandra cluster

Environment: Docker, Maven, Microservices, Java, Spring, AngularJS, Bamboo, RPM, Linux, HPSA, Zenoss, AngularJS, NodeJS, ELK, Graphite, Sensu

Independent Project

April to July 2014

Paris, France

AboWeb

Transat, company developing the subscription management web application AboWeb, appealed to Mr. Argenson and his knowledge in Web and JavaServer Faces (JSF) development to migrate their presentation layer to JSF 2.0 and PrimeFaces. That project was done in parallel of the employment at Nuance, mostly during weekends.

Environment: Java, JSF, PrimeFaces, jQuery, IntelliJ

Sologlobe Logistique

Montreal, Quebec January 2014

Developer

In a ten-person team, Mr. Argenson contributes to the development of Solochain, the Warehouse Management System (WMS) developed by Sologlobe.

Main Missions:

- Integration of Solochain with Microsoft Dynamics AX and other ERP
- Implementation of automated testing and Behavior Driven Development (BDD)
- Customization for various customers (Domino's Pizza, Fona International, Analog Devices, ...)
- Migration of the Source Management System from CVS to Git
- Internal training about new tools (Unit Tests, BDD, Continuous Integration and Git)

Environment: Java, Spring, JPA, JUnit, Mockito, Cucumber, Selenium, Jenkins, Ant, Ivy, SQL Server, Git

SUPINFO International University

November 2010 to May 2013

July 2013 to

Paris, France

Full Professor and Developer

Mr. Argenson acted as a Full Professor of all the courses on 34 campuses worldwide about Java, Web and Agile Software Development. He managed a team of about 60 trainers.

He also acted as Software Developer for the Global Academic Department of the school.

Full Professor Missions:

- Validation, training and mentorship of the trainers
- Creation of the learning contents and courses scenarios
- In charge of the partnerships with some IT companies specialized in Software Development
- Mentorship of the new Full Professors

Main Software Developer missions:

Project: Note ton STA

"Note ton STA" allows students and other external attendees to send feedback and suggestions to a trainer about a course or a conference.

Role: Lead developer

Environment: Java, Servlet, JSP, JPA, Google App Engine, Git

Project: TicketManager

A support ticket system to track and respond trainer support request about a course.

Role: Developer

Environment: Java, JSF 1.2, EJB 3, Hibernate/JPA, JUnit, Mockito, Arquillian, DBUnit, JBoss, Cloudbees,

Jenkins, Maven, Git

Project: StatsMarks

Web application developed to compute some statistics about students' marks and build analysis based on them.

Role: Lead Developer

Environment: Java, Play! Framework, JQuery, MongoDB, Heroku, Git

Independent Project

May to June 2012

Paris, France

T'écoutes Quoi? (tecoutesquoi.com)

T'écoutes Quoi? is a dating site by musical affinity born from the idea of a four-person team during a *Startup Weekend* contest in Paris. Mr. Argenson developed on the project until the first prototype of the website, then left the team for other projects. The website is currently available in Beta.

Environment: Java, Play! Framework, JQuery, Facebook OpenGraph API, LastFM API

Independent project

February to March 2011

Paris, France

Liquidation Locale

Mr. Argenson developed in a four-person team an Android application to find geo-localised promotions and clearances. The application was developed for the *BeMyApp* contest and was chosen by the jury as the best application idea.

Environment: Java, JAX-RS/Jersey, Hibernate/JPA, Android, SVN, Google App Engine

Xebia IT Consulting

May to November 2010

Paris, France

Consultant

Xebia is an IT consultancy organization, specialized on Java Technologies and Agile business change management.

Mission:

Project: Plastic Omnium Environment

Plastic Omnium Environment is the world's leading provider of waste containerization products and services. The mission was to develop a new billing application based on a rules engine with a custom DSL (Domain Specific Language).

Role: Developer

Environment: Java, Flex, Spring, Hibernate/JPA, Groovy, JUnit, EasyMock, DBUnit, Tomcat, Maven,

Jenkins, SVN, Scrum

Duration: 6 months

Atos Worldline
Seclin, France
October 2009
to May 2010

Developer

Mr. Argenson worked as a developer for the Bank, Finance and Insurance Business Unit of Atos Worldline. In a twelve-person team, he developed a specific module, taking place inside the Atos financial platform used by some famous European banking group (Boursorama Group, BNP Parisbas, ...).

Mission:

Module: Alert Engine

Analysis, design and development of an alert engine based on technical analysis.

Role: Developer

Environment: Java, Tomcat, JUnit, SOA, SVN

Duration: 6 months

SYLIS June to October 2009

Lille, France

Developer

Mr. Argenson worked as a Java developer for SYLIS, a French information technology service provider.

Missions:

Internal Project: Monthly Records of time

Analysis, design and development of a new module in the HR Platform to manage monthly records of time worked by consultant and by client.

Role: Developer

Environment: Java, Struts, Spring, JDBC

Duration: 3 months

Customer Project: Securex

Securex is a Belgian company specialized on HR Services. Mr. Argenson acted on the redesign of the medical control software as Continuous Integration consultant and introduces automated functional tests.

Role: Developer

Environment: Java, Maven, Hudson, Selenium, JUnit, Weblogic

Duration: 2 months

Audaxis
Lille, France
to May 2009

Developer

Mr. Argenson worked as a developer for Audaxis, a European information technology service provider.

Mission:

Project: www.lavoixauto.com

Corrective maintenance and evolution of the web application specialized in auto and motorcycle ads.

Role: Developer

Environment: Java, Spring, Hibernate/JPA, Struts 2, Maven, MS SQL Server, JBoss AS

Duration: 6 months

Webpulser
Roubaix, France

November 2008

Web Developer

Webpulser is a French web agency specialized on e-commerce and interactive websites.

Missions:

Project: Finaref (cliquez-achetez.finaref.fr)

Developed a Web application to highlight Finaref's partner products.

Role: Developer

Environment: Ruby on Rails, JQuery

Duration: 2 months

Project: The Sphere (the-sphere.com)

Developed a luxury social network, where only the most eligible people are accepted as members.

Role: Developer

Environment: Ruby on Rails, JQuery

Duration: 4 months

EDUCATION

Master in Computer Science SUPINFO International University, Lille	2010
CERTIFICATIONS	
Oracle Certified Web Component Developer for Java EE 5 Paris, France	2010
Sun Certified Programmer for Java 6 Lille, France	2009
MCP: Developing and Implementing Windows-Based Applications with C# .NET Paris, France	2009
Novell Certified Linux Administrator for SUSE Linux Enterprise 10 Lille, France	2008
CONFERENCES	

JS.Everywhere(2012) 2012

Paris, France

Workshops animation about HTML5 and JavaScript programing.

PUBLICATIONS AND PRESENTATIONS

Translation in French of the Book *Getting Value out of Agile Retrospectives* written by *Luis Gonçalves* and *Ben Linders*:

- http://www.infoq.com/minibooks/agile-retrospectives-value [en]
- https://leanpub.com/gettingvalueoutofagileretrospectives_FR [fr]

Java and Web development courses realized for SUPINFO International Campus and published on iTunes U:

https://www.google.ca/search?q=site%3Aitunes.apple.com+%22by+Brice+ARGENSON%22

Some other presentations about code quality, good practices for software development and a return of experience about implementing a DSL for the business are available on my *Slideshare*:

http://www.slideshare.net/bargenson

A ready to use / easy to use Monitoring stack running with Docker, composed of Logstash/Kibana Graphite/Grafana and Sensu/Uchiwa: https://github.com/Nuance-Mobility/Hera-Monitoring